I would say the two things that have
helped me in that exam that have helped
me most of my law enforcement career my
grandmother instilled in me two things
problem solving being a big part of that
is is like you never make excuses when
bad things happen don't make excuses you
put yourself in that position you found
yourself here it is nobody else's fault
but yours you know I'm not an excuse
person I don't make excuses if I find
myself in a bad situation I did
something to get myself here and I'm
going to get myself out and that was the
way she taught. The other thing she
taught me was she's like, "You're going
to be damned if you do and damned if you
don't. You better be damned for doing
[clears throat] like so [laughter] you
act. You always act. You don't let your
circumstances
dictate for you. You act and you take
action and you do. You don't wait for
somebody else to do for you."
>> Kathy, it is so lovely to see you and
thanks for making the time. Really nice
to see you again.
>> Glad to finally connect. It was nice to
see you, too, Tim. I was going back and
forth on where to start this and I think
I'm just going to follow the tried
andrue and begin at the beginning here
and maybe we should just start with
tuxedo and just give people sort of a
snapshot
[gasps] of
where you grew up, how you grew up, you
know, all those dreams of being in law
enforcement. And [laughter]
I'm partially kidding, of course,
because I know a little bit of the
backstory, but can you tell people
about the beginning?
>> It's important, I think, for context
about the choices I made in my life,
like everybody on this planet, the way
you're raised, your your family, your
environment has so much influence on the
way you do things as an adult. So, my
parents married right after high school.
First boyfriend, girlfriend, you know,
so right after high school. My father
was a firefighter, went in the fire
department. My mother was a secretary.
She went to work for the federal
government.
Dream, you know, back in the 50s, being
married at 18 is perfectly normal. So,
they got married, bought a home, started
having children, they had three kids.
I'm the youngest of the three. After I
was born, I think they realized that a
secretary and a firefighter salary does
not exactly cover child care for three
kids. So, they couldn't afford the child
care for three kids for both of them to
work. So, my mother took a a leave of
absence from work. She did eventually go
back, but she took a 10-year leave of
absence after I was born. And then when
I was two, my mother took us to my
grandparents for the weekend. And when
we came home, my father was gone. He had
taken a car [clears throat]
and uh left my mom with three kids and
and no income literally cuz she was not
working at the time. So, life changed
pretty dramatically for us. Then I was
again, I was two. I don't remember a lot
of detail early on, but I do remember as
a child growing up over that next 10
years, my mom was home with us really
just a wonderful childhood. My mother
was always there. She helped with
homework and she would take me to soccer
practice and basketball practice and
majorette practice. I mean, she was
always with us and she was just a a
wonderful, loving, caring mom. And we
didn't have a lot, you know, we lived on
$350 a month. my my father's eventually
paid child support. So, we had, you
know, a lot of support from the church
and from, you know, friends and family.
But it was a a fun childhood for me. I
mean, my mom was with me and I I think
she provided a lot of stability for my
brothers and I. And then when I was
getting ready to go from back then, this
is back before middle school. So, you
went, you know, elementary school,
junior high school, high school. So, in
sixth grade, you leave elementary school
and you go to junior high school. So
>> I was 12 years old, 13 years old,
becoming a teenager. We were going to a
new school. I was going to seventh
grade. My mother went back to work. I
was the youngest at the time at 13. She
felt like we were old enough to be latch
key kids and come home and let us in,
you know, be home for a couple hours
every day until she got home from work.
So she went back to work in her same
role working for her same boss that she
left 10 years earlier, which is pretty
amazing.
>> That is amazing. In fact, that whole
10-year period when my mother was off,
also important is how it frames my
context of things is during that 10
years when my mom was home. I remember
her sitting in front of the TV and
taking shortorthhand to the television
and she would like get our favorite
records and she would write down in
shorthand all the words and then she
would sit at the table and type them all
up and give us the words so we could
sing along with our songs. And you know,
I thought it was just mom doing fun
things for us, but it was her keeping
her skills, right? My mom when she went
back to work after a 10-year break in
service, she still took shorthand at
like 96 words a minute and still could
type over 100 words a minute. So,
>> wow.
>> Just a wonderful example of work ethic
for us. She knew she needed to go back
to work and wanted to go back to work as
soon as possible and she wanted to be on
her game. So, great childhood. But when
I was moving to junior high school, my
mom went back to work. So, I kind of
lost that guardian, that best friend
like at a critical time, right? Like I'm
becoming a teenager. We were going to a
new school. They were busing back in
those days. So, I was being busted into
a really tough neighborhood in
Washington DC.
>> From Maryland to Washington DC.
>> Right on the border of DC.
>> Can I pause you for one second?
>> Sure.
>> I'm just trying to put myself, which is
impossible for me to do of course, in
your mom's shoes, right? You guys return
to the house, no car, dad's gone, three
kids. Have you spoken to her or do you
have any best guesses as to the other
things that helped her
hold everything together in terms of
resilience or support or anything else?
I mean, I suppose that necessity is the
mother of invention on some level, but
have you ever spoken to her about that?
>> I did. And you know, it's funny. My
mother was very passive, sweet, just
kind of a very quiet internal person.
>> And in my entire life, I never saw my
mother cry. Never. Never. I mean, under
any circumstances when I I'm sure she
did.
>> Mhm.
>> But I never really saw my mother cry.
And my grandmother was completely the
opposite. My mom was an only child. Her
mother was like a pistol. Like hardcore.
So my grandmother was very helpful, but
my mother was a rock. I mean, she took
care of us. When I tell people now, we
lived on food stamps, welfare. The
church brought us baskets of food for
the holidays, but we didn't have a car
for many years. We finally got a car. It
didn't have heat. It used to break down
every time we went out in it. You know,
the hot water spet in our bathroom used
to squirt scalding hot water over you if
you didn't weren't careful because it
needed a washer and there was nobody to
come and fix that washer, you know. So,
but we had a wonderful childhood. My
mother was just solid. She loved her
kids and she was a beautiful, beautiful
woman. And I always ask her why she
didn't ever date and she's like, "My
kids were my life and I didn't want
anybody around my children that didn't
think of them as the same priority that
I thought of them." So,
>> I think her resilience was really just
steady for her family. I think her
family was her motivation and nothing
was going to disrupt her commitment
there.
>> Yeah. The singular focus. So, I
interrupted you.
>> That's okay. you were saying there's
this transition point. You're busing in
to Washington DC and
you've sort of lost your guardian in a
sense.
>> Yeah.
>> At that point. So if if you wouldn't
mind picking up there.
>> So again, we were being busted into a
neighborhood. The idea at the time was
to racially integrate neighborhoods. I
lived in a very small industrial
neighborhood, like an industrial park
right on the border of Washington DC.
Literally, there was a train that ran
right behind my house in the backyard.
On the other side of that train tracks
was Washington DC. We were on the
Maryland side. So, they were busing us
to a school and uh on the border of
northeast Washington to integrate, you
know, racially integrate the schools.
So, each day when our bus would pick us
up and take us to school, when our bus
would pull up in front of the school,
everything in most big cities, I would
say, but in Washington for sure, is very
neighborhood based. So when our bus
would pull up in front of the school and
we would get out as the Maryland kids
coming to the school, as soon as we'd
get off the bus, we'd get jumped. Like
every day there was a fight.
[clears throat] It was a terrible
change. You know, all the way through
school. I was in the talented and gifted
program, straight A student, loved
school, and now I'm being busted into a
school where the kids that we were going
to school with hated us. Was very
racially charged. It was agonizing to go
to school because you had to fight just
to get from the bus to the classroom. So
my mom would go, her bus would, it's
funny now, it wasn't funny then, but her
bus would pick her up on the corner at
7:00 in the morning and my bus would
pick me up on the other corner at 7:15.
So we'd both go out to the bus stop
together in the morning and she would
wait for her bus, I'd wait for my bus.
She'd get on her bus and she'd ride by
me and I'd wave and then one of my older
friends who had a car would come and
pick me up and we would go skip school
for the day. You know, I at least would
skip the first half. Like I would skip
the first few periods so I didn't have
to go through that agonizing, you know,
fight every morning
>> entry.
>> Yeah.
>> Rough entry.
>> So I went from, you know, a talented and
gifted student with straight A's to
failing like literally every subject the
first quarter of seventh grade. So I was
chronically truent. I think I was
averaging 19 days a quarter that I was
actually showing up for school. My
mother didn't know because the school
never notified her. And by the time she
got home from work at 6:00 p.m., we were
all sitting around like pretending to do
our homework. So my poor mother had no
idea until about midway through the
eighth grade, I was so chronically
truent that I was failing all of my
major subjects. So meanwhile, while I'm
skipping school, I'm hanging out with
the wrong people. Much older crowd,
friends of my older brother and older,
you know, just an older crowd and just
getting in trouble. and I fall in love
with a much older boyfriend at the time,
think I'm in love and we want to get
married and run away and get married.
And so by the time I was in the ninth
grade, I 14 years old, found myself
pregnant. My boyfriend at the time had
given me a diamond ring. We were
engaged. We're going to get married. So
we run away. He was 26 at the time. I
was 14. My mother, when she finds out,
was going to have him arrested, right?
So she was going to put him in jail. So,
I run away from home and think, "Well,
we got this. We're going to get married
and we're going to have the baby and
everything's going to be great."
The mind of a 14-year-old.
Obviously, things didn't work out that
way. So, interestingly, I went to my
father, who had been out of the picture
most of my life, and asked for him to
sign for me to get married because I had
to, because of my age, one of my parents
had to legally sign over my legal
guardianship to my husband.
>> [clears throat]
>> So they literally signed over my legal
guardianship to my husband. So my dad
thinking he would have one less child to
pay child support for cuz once he signed
over my guardianship he
>> and cuts the child support bill
>> paid $100 less a month in child support.
So he signed over my legal guardianship
to my husband. We got married the day
after my 15th birthday. I was 8 months
pregnant at the time. So, I guess fast
forward a little bit, a year and a half
later, I was back at home. My mother was
taking me to GED classes at night. I was
sneaking to go to GED classes when I was
still married. My husband didn't approve
of me going to school. So, once we
separated, my mom made sure I stayed in
school, got my GED. She would bring her
typewriter home from work and she taught
me how to type on the kitchen table. So,
she taught me how to type and take a
little shortorthhand. And I went and got
a job as a secretary. I lied about my
age. I went and got a job as a secretary
when I was 16. So started working as a
secretary and then worked as a waitress
in the evening in a bar. Also lied about
my age to work in a bar. That was the
only option up in the area where I was
working. So for the next several years,
I worked two jobs as a secretary and a
waitress. You know, my motivation
really was my son. Mhm.
>> It was
kind of a significant moment for me and
I've had a few in my life. When my son
was born, I'd never babysat before. I'd
never held a baby. I didn't know
anything about babies or children. And
when he was born, he was such a good
baby. His crib was at the end of my bed
in my bedroom. And I'd wake up in the
morning and he'd be awake and he'd just
be looking at me, waiting for me to wake
up, right? Not crying, [clears throat]
not nothing. He would just be looking at
me. [laughter]
And so
>> that is remarkable.
>> Yeah. About three weeks into this
experiment, I'm looking at him one
morning and it just dawns on me like for
the first time that I'm a parent and
that that helpless little baby was
completely relying on me. And my mother
was always stressed the importance of
education and work to us. And here I
was, you know, my husband didn't allow
me to go to school. I would never be
able to get a job. And I'm looking at
this poor little innocent baby and I'm
thinking, his whole life depends on me.
and what am I going to be able to
provide with a nth grade education and
not much.
So that was a aha moment.
>> Yeah. Yeah. I'm going to resist the
temptation to ask 300 questions about
the last few minutes that you shared
because we'll we'll end up spending all
of our time there if I do that. But I am
curious for you. I'm trying to put
myself
in your shoes at that young age.
when you and we we don't need to get
into the details unless you'd like to
share, but when you separated from your
then husband, like when that happened,
what did you think was going to become
of you? Like what did you envision
your path would be at that point? I have
to imagine that it would have just been
incredibly challenging. I don't know.
You can't believe everything you read on
the internet, but I read that when you
were a young girl, you dreamed of being
a lawyer. I don't know if that's true or
not.
>> And then flash forward, you go through
this entire tumultuous experience and
you land back at home. Where did you
think your life was headed? Where did
you think you were headed at that point?
Well, I knew that with a ninth grade
education and a single mom that I had
zero chance of being able to do what I
thought was most important in the world,
and that's take care of my son. And when
I first moved back home, I got my GED,
but I still was not able to easily find
a job at my age. I was, you know, 16,
almost 17. I had to wait till I was 16
and nine months to take the test to get
the GED.
>> Interestingly, you needed 255 to pass
the test. I got 256. I passed at that
one point.
>> Oh my god.
>> Just another little like footnote of my
life.
>> Talk about these sliding door moments.
Holy cow. Right.
>> So, my mother had always stressed the
importance of education and work. So, I
knew I had to go back to school and I
wanted to go to college. I didn't want
my son to be subject to the same crappy
neighborhoods and the same crappy
schools that I went to. I wanted him to
have a real chance. And I knew if I was
going to do that, I had to go back to
school and get a college education. And
if I didn't do that, he would be doing I
was standing in the same food stamp line
my mother stood in with me. I remember
the first day I went to get food stamps
going to the big white building by
Prince George's Plaza right near my home
and standing in the same line with my
son that I stood in with my mom when I
was a kid and I was like this is not my
path. This can't be my path. And when I
got my job as a secretary, they offered
tuition reimbursement to go to college.
So, I started a community college. I
just started taking one class a semester
and uh that's where it started, one
class a semester and they reimbured me
for it. So, [laughter and snorts]
>> so I recall I mean for people who don't
have contacts, we've been we've been
trying to schedule this for a while and
understandably you got a lot of balls to
juggle and
I remember hearing just pieces of your
story. This was God, it has to be what,
more than a year ago now. I'm sure. Time
flies, but it's been a it's been a long
while. And I just remember thinking to
myself, God, I hope someday that we can
have this conversation on the podcast.
So, I want to thank you again for doing
it. How do you then go from there? What
is the connective tissue sort of the
catalyzing events that ultimately get
you into law enforcement? Right? What is
what are the first few dominoes that get
tipped over that start to push you in
that direction?
>> So, to be fair, my family is a public
service family. My father was
firefighter. My oldest brother had
become a firefighter right out of high
school. My other [clears throat] brother
was a police officer. I was working as a
secretary. I was taking that one class a
semester working as a secretary trying
to get my son in private school. I
wanted him in private school. I did not
want him going to those schools. I was
still living in the same crappy
neighborhood, but I wanted my son in a
good school. And I saw an ad. I was 23
years old. I saw an ad in the Washington
Post for the Metropolitan Police
Department. They were hiring. And what
caught my attention, it's a full page ad
in the post. The half of the page was
said tuition reimbursement. I'm like,
"Oh my god, tuition reimbursement. I'm
paying for one class a semester. I'm
going to take me 30 years to get a
degree."
>> So I went with a friend and we went and
stood in line. They were hiring a
thousand cops. This was during the crack
cocaine wars in Washington. Early 1990.
So 500 murders a year. DC was known as
the murder capital of the world at the
time. So I just went and stood in line
with a thousand other people. Went and
took the test and I came out I want to
say I came out like 60 out of a thousand
people on that test. So they called me
right away. I was the only white female
in the room. Right. This is back in the
early 90s. Washington DC was about 89%
African-American. Right. So I felt the
same drive my mother felt taking care of
us is that I have a son that needs me.
He needs me to provide for him and the
only way I'm going to do this is get a
good job. Government job, not a bad
option, and go back to school and get my
degree. So I got hired by the
Metropolitan Police in 1990. Started
walking a footbeat. My first day out of
the academy was the Mount Pleasant
riots. So my first day out of the
academy, I went to work and didn't come
home for 5 days. It was great. Okay,
we're gonna double click on that and
come right back to Mount Pleasant. But
before we do,
>> I want to know what the entrance exam or
qualification exam was like.
>> Mhm.
>> Right. because you you mentioned the GED
and like just by sort of the skin of
your teeth getting in, you know, passing
the hurdle and then it sounds like you
not very technical term, but kind of
crushed the
the examination that you took that
ultimately placed you at 60 out of a
thousand. What was that test like?
>> So, remember now when I started going
taking classes at Prince George's
Community College, my goal was to be a
lawyer. I wanted to be an attorney.
>> Mhm. I started out wanting to be a
secretary like my mom. Then once I got
into the workplace, I realized I wanted
bigger, better things. So I wanted to be
an attorney. So I was taking political
science, philosophy, a lot of those kind
of courses, getting all my generals out
of the way in community college. So by
the time I got to the Metropol Police
Department at 23, I had three years of
college courses, right?
>> But the exam for entry into policing,
now back in those days, they only
required a high school diploma or an
equivalent. So you didn't need college.
So the this the entry exam was a lot of
things that you would expect for law
enforcement. You do a lot of multiple
choice questions. You know, you have to
be able to read and comprehend well. So
reading comprehension was a big part of
it. You have to do some basic math,
right? So you have to understand math.
But there was a lot of problem solving
type questions. So they flash a photo in
front of you and then they say you
there's a photo inside of a a department
store. Okay. you just walked into this
department store and there's been a
robbery, right? What is it you noticed
in that quick three seconds you had to
look at that photo? What do you
remember? What time was it on the clock?
You know, what color was the lady's
shoes that was standing at the register?
Right? Like,
>> so there was, you know, reading
comprehension, math, problem solving,
and then a good bit of are you paying
attention? you have the detail to pay
attention and do the things that you
need to do as a police officer, which
much of which you learn as a cop.
>> But it seems like you had either
developed or innately possessed,
and maybe I'm reaching, but I mean,
maybe not. I mean, was there anything in
that test that highlighted,
[snorts] for lack of a better
descriptor, like superpowers, strengths
of yours that came into like full
fruition later where you're like, okay,
if I look at the recipe, some of the
ingredients of the recipe that
ultimately contributed to my success,
were any of them sort of revealed in
that test in any way or not really?
>> Great question. Actually, it's a very
good question. I don't get a lot of
interviews that ask the types of
question you're asking. I think it's a
excellent question. So I I would say the
two things that have helped me in that
exam that have helped me most of my law
enforcement career. My grandmother
instilled in me, you know, she spent a
lot of time with us growing up as well.
Two things, problem solving being a big
part of that is is like you never make
excuses. When bad things happen, don't
make excuses. You put yourself in that
position. You found yourself here. it is
nobody else's fault but yours. You know,
I'm not an excuse person. I don't make
excuses. If I find myself in a bad
situation, I did something to get myself
here and I'm going to get myself out.
And that was the way she taught. You get
yourself in, you get yourself out. And
the other thing she taught me was she's
like, you know, you're going to be
damned if you do and damned if you
don't. You better be damned for doing.
[clears throat] Like, so you act.
>> You always act. You don't let your
circumstances
dictate for you. you act and you take
action and you do. You don't wait for
somebody else to do for you. And those
things were really part of that
problem-solving exercise when you're
coming on the police department. And
it's certainly your problem solving
exercise every day you're on the police
department.
>> Mhm.
>> It it certainly was for the next 27
years for me. You can't avoid
consequences. There's consequences for
everything that happens. Every decision
you make has consequences. You can't
avoid consequences, but you can choose
what you do after those things happen.
I imagine you've probably not met him,
but I interviewed someone named Jaco
Willink, who's a former Navy Seal
commander many years ago. It was the
first time he ever did a public
interview. And he wrote a book called
Extreme Ownership. And I feel like your
grandmother and what she instilled in
you is in a nutshell exactly the type of
high agency thinking that Jaco talks
about. It's the same thing.
>> Yeah.
>> Wow.
>> My grandma would say there there's two
types of people in the world. Excuse
people and people who are accountable.
And I'm going to be the accountable.
>> Let's come back to Mount Pleasant. For
people who don't have the historical
context, what were the Mount Pleasant
riots? And you said right before I asked
about the test, you said it was great.
And if that is actually not a sarcastic
statement, but a real sort of statement
of how you felt, I want to know why that
was the case. But let's start with just
a little bit of
>> history for people who who aren't
familiar. I certainly wasn't with the
Mount Pleasant riots
>> when I said it was great in terms of
being a rookie right out of the academy
and understanding what you've got
yourself into, right?
>> It was here's what you've got yourself
into, right? Like you went to work today
and you're not gone home for 5 days, you
know? So the night before my first day
out of the academy, there was a pair of
police officers walking a foot patrol in
in our patrol district. They tried to
place a gentleman under arrest for
drinking in public. He was a Latino
male, didn't speak English. We had a big
problem in our city back in those days.
Law enforcement, we had very few people
in the department that spoke Spanish. We
had a huge Latino population. There was
a big gap in our community. So, it's
really difficult to do any kind of
effective policing if you're not
communicating with the people in the
community, and we were not. So when this
officer was trying to place this person
under arrest during the handcuffing the
the subject after one handcuff was on he
turned around pulled the knife on the
officer and the officer shot. So he was
shot with one handcuff on so the partner
of the officer who shot rolled him over
put the other handcuff on took the knife
away called paramedics. Alls that people
saw was a handcuffed person who'd been
shot. M
>> so the Latino community in that
neighborhood immediately began, you
know, gathering on the street, large
crowd. This all happened around 11:30 at
night. So by the time I got into the
station for 5:30 roll call, I show up at
5:30 in the morning. The riot had broken
out around 1:00 a.m. They had burned
several police cars. There was stores
that were looted and on fire. I mean,
there was a big, big deal down in Mount
Pleasant. So when I got to work my first
day, I walked into the station, said,
"Hi, I'm Kathy Laneir. I'm the, you
know, new rookie from the academy." And
they threw me a gas mask and they told
me to go out and get in the van. He
said, "Hop over the counter, go out the
back door and get in that van." And I
was like, "Okay."
So I hopped over the counter and went
and got in that van. I was sitting with
15 other cops with gas mask on and big
riot sticks and they took us down and
they dumped us off on the corner of
Mount Pleasant and Park Road and it was
fully engulfed in a fires and looting
and you know people were throwing
bottles and bricks and stones at us. We
had little helmets they had given us in
the as we were hopping out of the van
and I didn't have a radio because
rookies weren't allowed to have radios
at the time, right? I had not been
trained how to use the radio. So my
partner had the radio. So my lifeline
was on my partner, but we stood there
online and literally got pelted with
bricks and bottles and I mean over the
course of 5 days. It was trial by fire
for sure. But it was a big learning
experience for me because I understood
the frustration. I understood the
frustration. The large number that whole
community of Mount Pleasant were all
Latino. They didn't speak English. The
cops didn't speak to them very well. I
mean, nobody could really communicate
with, but the cops were pushing people
around and there was no way to to try
and get the story straight and really no
effort to get the story straight, right?
To understand the frustration. So, it
was a big learning experience for me as
I worked my way up the ranks to
understand how important inclusion is in
the community. If you're a police
officer and you are not embedding
yourself in that community and
understanding who the people are in that
community and what their needs are and
how to communicate, you're really not
going to be successful.
>> We're gonna, I imagine, revisit that at
some point because it seems to be a
consistent thread through a lot of the
work they've done. But I want to spend a
little bit more time on Mount Pleasant.
I am curious, I suppose, yet again, what
that
maybe showed you about yourself or just
highlighted about you constitutionally
or personalitywise, right? Because I
would imagine some people could get
dropped in that environment after they
just signed up. They're like, "Hey, I'm
just here for tuition reimbursement.
Holy shit." Like, I'm getting hit with
bricks. Like, this is not exactly what I
thought my first day was going to be.
and they're out, right? Like I have to
imagine that there are some people who
would be closer to that. Maybe they
didn't quit, but they're probably closer
to that end of the spectrum.
And do you thrive in particular in
intense environments? I wonder, right?
Because like in my case,
constitutionally sort of out of the box,
little things, especially interpersonal
things bother me that are kind of
trivial, frankly. Like I get all wound
up about very stupid things, but in
crisis situations,
you know, the car accident in front of
me, some guy's got his like leg blown
apart or whatever. I actually do really
I do very well in those environments. I
don't know why that is. I really have no
idea. Yeah.
>> But was there anything that you noticed
about yourself in that type of
environment in those types of
circumstances? I think the thing for me
that I thrive on is as we're dropped out
down there and they're giving us the
riot sticks and the helmets and the gas
mask and they're shooting canisters of
gas into the crowd and knowing what
started this and how this all blew up.
I'm thinking to myself, we're not going
about this the right way. Like I was a
rookie. I know nothing about policing
other than what I was taught in the
academy. So by no means did I think I
was smarter than the guy making the
command decisions, right? But I'm just
looking at it from my perspective and
going this is just not the right way to
do this. like this is we're not going to
win here. That's this is not a win
situation. This should be done
differently. And I just always felt like
from the minute I hit the ground like
watching like analyze the way that we
were doing things and thinking why are
we doing this this way? There's a better
way to do these things. And so that's
the way I felt at Mount Pleasant my
first day on the job. You know, really
hard to explain. I just felt like
there's a problem to be solved here and
we're not going about it in a problem
solving manner. We're going about it
with brute force, right? brute force
doesn't always work.
>> So, it intrigued me. Every day after
that, once the riots were over, I
started walking a footbeat in the city.
Every single day I went to work, I got
to problem solve for
six, seven, eight times a day, you know,
and calls for service, 911 calls. You
respond to people who are in crisis,
people who need help, and you know, you
get to try and help think through that,
help solve the problem. And that's
that's what I enjoyed doing. It's
frustrating when you're at the bottom of
the totem pole and you're the line
officer, right? you're in a chain of
command. You can't make certain
decisions. But I did feel like every
single day I went to work, I made a
difference in someone's life,
>> no matter how small.
>> Yeah. And this was around, tell me if
I'm getting this wrong, but around 1990
or early early 90s.
>> 1990.
>> Yep. 1990.
>> And you were working your way up the
ranks. When did you first and we'll
certainly talk about kind of the the
good, the bad, and the ugly of that time
frame
in some respects, but when did your
first real mentor show up? I have
different names from doing homework in
front of me. I've got, if I'm saying it
correctly, you know, Sonia Proctor,
[snorts] I've got Charles Ramsay, who
might show up a little bit later. I'm
not sure exactly on the chronology, but
were there any critical figures in the
first few years who were helpful to you
or was it really just executing, getting
the job done, delivering and working
your way up? I'm wondering when your
first mentor of sorts or kind of
[snorts]
I don't want to say guardian, it might
not be the right word, but influential
figure showed up within policing.
>> So, I was an officer and I loved my job.
I got once I worked my way up, I was
foot patrol the first, you know, several
months and then I went to motorcycle
school and I got trained to ride a motor
and then I was on a motorcycle. I want
to be mobile so I could get around and
you know I love the adrenaline 911 calls
getting out there being first on the
scene and and then I got moved up a
little bit more and seniority and I was
in a patrol car and I used to get on the
radio and I'm like all right dispatcher
I'm in service give me stack me up give
me all the calls you got pending you
know that's been sitting there waiting I
I'll take them all. I had a lieutenant
who he was like a SWAT team commander
guy who got promoted to lieutenant and
they sent him out to patrol which is
like a slap in the face to a SWAT guy,
right?
>> For sure.
>> Like they hate the patrol stuff. But
he'd come to my district and he called
me in his office one day. He's like, "I
hear you on the radio out there." He's
like, "You're really humping." I was
like, "Yeah, I love this job. This is
great. It's fun." And he's like, "You're
coming up on three years. You're going
to be eligible for sergeant. You should
take that sergeant's test." And I was
like, "Why would I do that? I like my
job. like what I'm doing if I take
sergeant test and I'm going to get moved
somewhere. He's like, "No, no, you need
to take the sergeants test." Like, well,
why would I want to do that? And he's
like, "Well, you want to make more
money, right?" And I'm like, "That's a
good point." And he said, "And once you
start taking these promotional exams, it
gives you more opportunities to
influence the things. You know, I hear
you're trying to change some things. You
know, why don't you take that exam?" So,
he pushed me pretty hard. And when the
tests announcement came out, he said,
"Come on, I'm going to give you a ride.
let's go pick up your books. You have a
eight-month window to study. He's like,
"Let's go pick up your books."
>> So, I was like, "All right." I was a
little intimidated. I like, "Okay." So,
I took that sergeant's test. I was
eligible for sergeant at 3 years. I took
the first sergeants and test. There was
890 people that were eligible that we
took the test all together. After the
written exam, you go to um an assessment
phase where you do a bunch of oral
interviews and exercises and paper
exercises. and I end up coming out
number 13 out of 890 for that. So I got
promoted right away. A very young
sergeant, 26 years old, three years on
the job. Most of the people I I had a
master patrol officer working for me
that had more years on the job than I
was old. He had 26 years on the job. I
was 26 years old.
>> So that was the first mentor and he
remained a mentor for me for most of my
career.
>> What was his name?
>> Donnie Axom. Donnie Axom.
>> These stories are so critical, right?
Because I mean people are self-made in
many respects and at the same time you
just have to wonder sometimes right if
if you didn't have these intervening
figures
>> nothing like your experience but I had a
pretty miserable public school
experience when I was growing up and
ultimately hadn't even thought of
private school and it was there was one
math teacher who was basically like you
need to get the hell out of here and I
was like yeah yeah yeah out of here to
where right and he just kept harping on
me and then there was one other person
who chimed And then I had two people and
I was like, "Oh, okay. Maybe I should
take a look at this." And it was just
like if that had not happened, who
knows, right? Just a lot of question
marks.
>> Critical. Those mentors are critical.
>> What does a sergeant do? I'm embarrassed
to admit that I have no idea. Like, what
does a sergeant do?
>> This is one of the things that police
departments do, right? Now that I'm in
the private sector, I wish the private
sector had similar structure. So, once
you make sergeant, you start as a
first-line supervisor. So they'll give
you eight people, eight to 10 people
that that you're responsible for. So
you're the squad sergeant. Like you have
a squad that's assigned to you. Those
eight to 10 people, they report to you.
So I'm responsible for making sure when
we pop out a roll call and we hit the
street that that my squad of eight is
doing what they're supposed to do.
They're clearing their calls. They're
taking reports like they're supposed to.
If they get in a situation where they
don't know what to do, they go over the
radio call for me. I go down and help
them work through that situation. And I
help teach them how to manage these
situations. So, you're first line
supervision. You're right there every
day on the street with the 911
responders and you're helping them
manage those calls and you're helping
them manage how to solve those problems.
You're signing arrest paperwork. You
know, if you make an arrest, wait a
minute, let me let me look at all the
probable calls you have here before we
put this person in handcuffs or if you
got the person in handcuffs when I get
on the scene, let's review what you got
here, right? Before we take somebody to
jail, let's make sure we we've met the
DC code, right? We know that you've got
a legitimate arrest here. You start
managing a small group and then the next
level is manager. Then you become a
lieutenant and then they give you like
40 people to manage and you start making
little bigger decisions. Now you're
scheduling, you're assigning, you're
working through warrants and things like
that. So it's a very gradual
progression.
In that time frame,
early 90s or just 90s I suppose at
large, what was it like being a woman in
the police force?
>> It was a really tough environment when I
first got there. There were a few days
in the very beginning when I was an
officer that you know the good thing
about the officer like when I got there
the department was
85 probably%
African-Amean. And the city was largely
89% African-American. So largely
African-American, certainly very few
white females. It was very few females.
So I would think we were about 11% women
on the department of 5,000. 5200 I think
when I came on size of our department.
So very few women, very few white women.
It's hard to think back to 199. Sexual
harassment was common place. Nobody
talked about it. Nobody cared about it.
It wasn't an issue. Like it just it it
happened every day and you just, you
know, you work through it. I grew up
with two older brothers, so I kind of
knew how to navigate it a little bit.
You know, I listened. My brothers gave
me advice how to deal with some of this.
The good thing is as an officer, you
very quickly establish yourself. And I
established myself as an officer early
on as a worker. Like, I came to work, I
did my job. I don't need anybody to do
me any favors. You don't need to look
out for me. I don't need a partner. I
can ride by myself. I'm good. Once I
made sergeant though, the harassment got
worse. I mean, I I had a lieutenant that
was really really sexually harassing. I
mean, not just me, but several women,
physical harassment. I mean, like
getting you in a on a midnight shift in
a sergeant's office and closing the door
and, you know, putting her hands on you
and things like that. And I remember
saying to my boyfriend at the time, I
was like, "You know what? I got real
thick skin. I could take all kinds of
comments. I don't mind any of that
stuff, but I'm not going to let people
put their hands on me. That's just not
going to happen." So the harassment was
pretty intense. It was a it was a really
tough environment.
>> So what happened?
>> I eventually
So I had a a lieutenant when I made
sergeant. I was sent over to um
southeast Washington. I was patrolling
in southeast. I had really a good squad.
I worked nights, permanent nights. So I
had a lieutenant that was harassing me
and some other women, but me pretty
intensely. calling me on the radio,
forcing me to drive him around, putting
me in his cruiser with them, making me
drive him around,
just not letting me do my job, constant
harassment, calling me on the radio,
bringing me to the office, make me drive
him somewhere, things like that. So, I
finally, after several times of asking
him to leave me alone, I finally filed a
sexual harassment complaint. He had put
his hands on me several times. So, I
filed a complaint and I remember going
down to the EEO office and filing this
complaint and they asked me to write a
list of anybody who had ever Well, first
of all, before I went down, my partner,
one of my fellow sergeants who was a a
black male officer said to me one day,
we were out riding together. The
lieutenant had called me in and my
partner said to me, the other sergeant
said, "How long are you going to let
this keep going on before you do
something about it?"
>> And I was like, "What are you talking
about?" He's like, "I hope you're
writing this stuff down. I hope you're
going to say something to somebody
because this can't go on like this."
Again, a man, not a woman, another male
police officer basically said to me, "If
you're not going to stand up for
yourself, nobody else is going to stand
up for you." And so when he said that,
it clicked and like he's trying to say
either you're going to allow this to
keep happening or you don't want it to
happen and you do something about it. So
I after that conversation, I filed this
complaint.
I list all the people who had witnessed
because my harasser made no no effort to
hide it. He made horrible comments and
grabbed women in front of others all the
time. So I listed 17 different witnesses
and they did the investigation and
literally I left the EEO office. I went
to court. I had court that day and I was
in court 20 minutes after I left the EEO
office from filing my complaint. My
harasser, the lieutenant, texted me on
my beeper, and we had beepers back then,
[clears throat] and said, "I know what
you're doing, and you're not going to
get away with this." Like, so it was
supposed to be confidential, but within
20 minutes of leaving the office, the
person who was doing my investigation
called him and told him that I had made
a complaint.
>> Gross.
>> So, I had to go back to work in that
environment, one of the most violent
areas of Washington DC. From that day
forward, he prohibited me from
partnering with anybody. He refused to
allow me to ride with anybody else. He
continued the harassment. He, you know,
came into my office the next day, shut
the door and said, "Look, I know that
what you're doing. You need to back
down. You need to withdraw this
complaint. You're not going to win."
They sustained the complaint. So, the
investigation, all the witnesses I
listed, they were all men. I didn't
think any of them would tell the truth.
Nobody wanted to go against us, a higher
ranking person. And every
[clears throat] single one of them told
the truth. They all wrote down what they
saw. They all not only talked about what
they saw him doing to me, but what they
saw him doing to other women. And I was
just shocked.
>> I [clears throat] always say to women,
you don't realize when you're in these
scenarios, decent men that observe these
things going on, they don't like it
either, right? They don't like it
either. And and those other men that I
was working with, they didn't like it
either. And some of them, this guy had
harassed their girlfriends or their
wives or, you know what I mean? So
that really made an impression on me
that so many of the men that I work with
stood up and did the right thing there.
So when when it was time for him to be
disciplined for this, when we got to
trial board, I walk into trial board for
the discipline to come down and they
told me they had to drop the whole case
and throw it out. And I'm like, why?
What happened? And they said, well, we
missed the 90 days. In the District of
Columbia, you have to bring discipline
within 90 days of the day that you knew
or should have known about the
misconduct. They sat on this
investigation till day 91 and then
turned it in. So, literally after all of
that, they threw the case out and they
said, "Well, we'll just transfer you.
Where do you want to be transferred to?"
I was like, "I don't want to be
transferred. I didn't do anything wrong.
I don't transfer me. Transfer him. I
didn't do anything." He later had
several other complaints come forward
and eventually was terminated for a
severe case with another multiple other
subordinates later on.
>> But I will [snorts] tell you this now,
everything above the rank of captain in
the police department is appointed,
right? You civil service exam for
sergeant, lieutenant, and captain. After
captain, it's appointed by the chief of
police. You're an appointed rank. And
you're also at will. So if you can get
appointed to inspector or commander, but
you also can get demoted with no cause
either. So I remember one of my mentors,
another mentor, a lieutenant, there was
a captain and a lieutenant that were
both good mentors to me there. The
captain of the two mentors I had there
pulled me aside after this complaint and
said, "You did the right thing. He's
been harassing women here for years and
somebody needed to stand up, so you did
the right thing." He said, "But just
know you'll never make it past the rank
of captain." because my that lieutenant
was very well connected at the time to
the chief of police. So very friendly
with the chief of police that whole
administration. So I said that's fine.
Like that's fine. I wasn't thinking, you
know, long-term longevity and promotion.
>> That actually ties into what I was going
to ask you because it strikes me as
an incredibly brave thing to do. I
imagine not everyone in your situation
would have done that. I mean, in fact,
they didn't, right? I imagine there's a
lot of fear around there could be a lot
of fear around the political or job, you
know, professional repercussions of
voicing something like that, especially
during a period when that was not
common.
>> Well, remember my driver in life, Tim,
if you think about this and harassers
work this way. My goal in life is to
take care of my son. I'm a single mom.
After he knew I made a complaint, he was
threatening my job. He was really making
it very difficult for me to come to
work. like it was terrifying to come to
work, you know, and I was fighting for
my job. I can't lose my job. I have a
son to take care of and I'm not going to
lose my job because somebody wants to be
a bully. And that's the motivation. It
was it was terrible. I was sick to my
stomach every day. I was going in the
bathroom and throwing up. I mean, it was
when I got to work and just every time I
heard his voice on the radio, it was
terrible for me. But I also couldn't
afford to lose my job. I was not going
to let somebody force me out of my goal.
I had a son to take care of, so I
couldn't afford that. I was going to
fight until I knew that I was safe.
>> Yeah. I mean, it's sort of focusing
forcing function, right? I mean, having
that singular priority. So, it seems
like I mean, the predictions about you
never rising above the rank of what was
it? Captain.
>> Captain
>> seems like that fellow wasn't exactly
the the Nostradamus of of predicting the
future. So could you walk us through
sort of how things
progressed and why were you able to
continue to excel? Did his prediction
just turn out to be completely false?
>> I think it would have been accurate. I I
tell you what it the stars aligned for
me. So I took sergeant test at three
years. I was eligible for lieutenant at
five. I took the lieutenant's test at
five years. I came in number one on that
test. I took the captain's test seven
years. I came in number three on that
test. So I got promoted bang bang bang.
three years, five years, seven years. I
was a captain for seven years. I would
have never gone past the rank of captain
in that current administration. And then
Mary and Barry gets arrested, our mayor.
>> Mary and Barry is taken out and replaced
by the control board. The control board
comes in 1998. I'm a captain at the
time. Mayor and Barry is now taken out
of play. The control board takes over.
They bring in Chuck Ramsay, an outsider
who knows nobody
>> in the department. He doesn't know
anybody. He's got no click. He's got no
boys.
>> Everybody's fresh. So, he comes in as
I'm lieutenant just making captain,
takes over the police department as a
complete outsider and is doing his
assessment of what officials, what
command level officials he wanted to
have on his team. And he appointed me
from the rank of captain to be an
inspector to take over a major narcotics
branch with less than eight years on the
job. I was 29, I think.
>> All right. Chuck makes his appearance.
Right. Okay. Charles Ramsey.
>> He's the next big mentor.
>> Yeah.
>> Yes.
>> Okay. So, just for my honestly my
personal curiosities, I really know
nothing about how
police
structures work, right? What is what is
a captain doing? And then what is an
inspector do if you don't mind?
>> So, again, this is where I think the
police gets right. You're you spend
three years as a patrol officer. You
make sergeant. You study really hard to
take the test. You make sergeant. You do
go through some schools. After you make
sergeant, you manage a small group. Then
you make lieutenant two years later. You
go through the exam process. You go
through some schools after that. And
then you manage a squad of like a
platoon of 40. So now you've got when I
was lieutenant, I had narcotics
officers, I had detectives, and I had
patrols.
>> How are those 40 people determined? Is
it based on neighborhood or some type of
sort of geographic area
>> at that time? It's done differently and
over the course of the years it's
changed but at that time it was
geographically. So I had a patrol
district and of that patrol district I
had one-third of that patrol district
and I managed every resource for that
part of the district. So all three
shifts I had day work, midnights,
evening shift all three shifts. Those
officers are split across those three
shifts and they covered all the
policing. So, not just the 911
responders, the guys in the in uniform
going to 911 calls, but also your
narcotics officers and your detectives
that follow up and investigate crimes.
>> This is Lieutenant. Am I getting that
right?
>> That's Lieutenant.
>> Okay. So, Lieutenant, is that the first
time where you're getting kind of the
decathletes exposure to all of these
different things?
>> Yes. Okay. And you're also getting
exposure to administration. So, part of
that exam, that promotional exam is
studying administration. You have to
learn administration. Like so if there
are municipal regulations that need to
be changed and I'm managing a large part
of the portion of the District of
Columbia and I see a municipal
regulation needs to be changed, I need
to know the process to petition to
change that municipal regulation. How do
I go about changing that law?
>> Because I I'm seeing firsthand the
impact it's having in our neighborhoods,
right? So,
>> so police administration starts to
become more and more important there.
>> I also now can start influencing policy.
>> I can influence policy for my little
piece of the world, right? Mhm.
>> I decide what my drug enforcement
tactics are going to be. I decide how
we're going to work in terms of doing
warrant service and things like that. So
that's where you first start to get a
better understanding of influencing how
policing actually is carried out.
>> Not to minimize the the prior steps, but
it sounds like the lieutenant role is a
very dense learning opportunity
just based on the description. And I
think the best role, the best rank on
the police farmer for me was lieutenant.
I was able to still go out on the
street, support my troops, back up my
sergeants, have fun policing and do the
policing that I enjoyed, but I also had
the ability to change the environment
for them, help them
>> and also influence how we were policing
our community.
>> And then captain,
>> after captain, it gets, you know, so
captain is more more you're strapped to
your desk a lot more. Yeah, I was going
to say more more behind the desk
>> because you're reviewing bad arrest that
went, you know, somebody didn't a
sergeant didn't do the right thing and
review the paperwork. Now you've got a
bad arrest that's got to be detention
journal. So you've got to review and
make that decision. You've got to set
things up at the courts. You've got to
look at all the disciplinary
investigations that come in. You know,
officers getting disciplined for things.
You got to make decisions about that.
You sit on trial boards, you know, who's
going to get disciplined, who's going to
get terminated. It's very
administrative. You're helping the
commander make decisions, you know,
community meetings, deployment
decisions, and it's not as much fun.
>> Yeah. [laughter]
Yeah. I don't I do I I know a few people
in in law enforcement, but mostly
military, former military guys. And I
mean, very similar, right? Some of these
guys, they just love being in the field,
and they're like, I got promoted. It's
like, I just don't know how I feel how I
feel about it. They're [laughter] like
very mixed.
>> Well, here's the big key. When I went to
go change my uniform, so you go to
property division. When you get
promoted, you walk off the stage, you
get your promoted, you get your your
birds or whatever you're getting, your
clusters or whatever. It's for your new
rank. You go to the property division,
you get your new rank insignia. When I
made captain and I went over to property
division to get my new rank in, they
said, "Turn in your handcuffs." And I
was like, "What? Turn in [laughter] my
handcuffs? What are you talking about?
You don't need those anymore." Like, uh,
you're not taking my handcuffs. I'm
going to keep my handcuffs. I'm right
here. [laughter] Right here.
>> I kept my gun belt, my handcuffs, my
extra magazines, all those things that
the administrative captains used to turn
in. I'm like, "No." Uhuh. I'm keeping
this stuff.
>> Yeah. [laughter]
>> So, let's come back to Chuck. And
because I'm so unfamiliar with the
internal workings, it's hard for me to
pick the next
sort of flash point, maybe a seinal
moment for you. There's a lot to pick
from. I'm not sure how to put them in
order. Not that they have to be in
order, but maybe tell me if there's
something that we should talk about
before this, but you mentioned Chuck,
right, pushing you to take tough
assignments.
Is
special operations division is that a
sensible place to hop to next or what do
you think is are we skipping some
important
important steps in between? when Chuck
came in and he initially put me in
charge. I'd only been a captain I want
to say four or five months and he kind
of did a clean out at the top like a lot
of that old boy network that was there
when he got there. They were all people
that were long past retirement. So he
pushed a lot of the command staff out.
So that made him push people up pretty
young in their career. So he pushed me
up to be the commander of major
narcotics branch as an inspector. Like I
said, just under eight years on, so I
was very young.
>> I'm trying to do the math. How old were
you then at that point?
>> So I want to say I was 30ish 30 31 at
Major Narcotics Branch.
>> Wow, man. That's amazing. That is a lot
of responsibility.
>> And so I went to major narcotics branch.
So I had major narcotics branch and
vehicular homicide. So I managed all the
vehicular homicide investigative units
there for just under two years. And then
he promoted me again to commander and I
took over a patrol district. the fourth
district where Mount Pleasant sits, the
patrol district I started in, I went
back now and I was the commander of that
patrol district. It was the largest
residential area in the in the city of
Washington. So I took over that
district. I ran that for two years and
then he shot away. He called me down to
his office and he says, "You know, I'm
thinking I'm going to send you to SOD."
It was 911 happens, right? 911 happens
the Friday after 911. He says,"I think
I'm going to send you to special
operations division." I was like, "You
know what? I love being the district
commander. I love working in 4D. This is
my goal was to retire as the commander
of 4D. Thanks, but I really like where I
am." And [clears throat] he's like, "Oh,
okay." And then two days later, a
teletype came out transferring me to
SOD. So, like it wasn't really asking
me. [laughter]
He's like, "Oh, oh, okay."
>> He's like, "That's a great story. Thank
you for that."
>> Funny, right? [laughter] Glad to hear
it.
So I took over special ops. Now special
operations division had never had a
woman in charge. So that in itself was a
little intimidating. But the one thing
that when you talk about mentors and I I
know you probably have experienced this
like many others is
what a mentor does for you is they lend
you confidence that you don't have. Like
Chuck
recognized that I didn't have the
confidence. I was like intimidated by
this sod thing. My guy was like, "Yeah,
no." That, you know, never had a woman
in charge. It's the predominantly male.
I always say it's the most testosterone
in the police departments in SOD, right?
It's the bomb squad, the SWAT team,
harbor, the marine unit, the helicopter
unit, aviation, horsemounted unit, K9,
civil disturbance unit, the presidential
protection unit. So, it's like nine or
10 different units. You know, your your
high-end stuff. So, anyway, he
recognized that I was intimidated by
that. And he's like, "Mm- you're going
to go and you're going to do it." He
sent me off to a bunch of schools. I
went to EOD schools, bombing schools. I
learned how to manage a bomb squad. I
learned how to manage a squat team. And
the people there were great. That was my
best assignment in my entire career. I
spent six years there after 911
recreating our special operations
division and turning it into a homeland
security and counterterrorism unit.
>> What made it so good for you, that
particular role?
>> Well, it was the most complex role I'd
ever held. Most of the units I I
managed, I had to manage three or four
different type of specialties. I had to
manage nine different specialties and
they were highly special. Sniper teams
on the SWAT teams, negotiations unit,
the bomb squad. We were just after 911
and we were trying to evolve our
department from a pre 911 police
department in the nation's capital to a
post 911 police department in the
nation's capital. We got called
flatfooted on 911 and we should not have
been. We didn't have the skills,
training, equipment, and things that we
should have had. Right? I always say
Timothy McVey, that Oklahoma City
bombing was the wakeup call. That's when
we should have started changing the way
we train and prepare our police
officers, but we didn't. Right? And then
there's the first World Trade Center
bombing. That was another wakeup call.
We didn't respond to that. It was not
until 911 that the nation's police
departments in the largest cities really
realized that we have to be prepared for
this type of asymmetric threat that
we're now facing. So when Chuck put me
in charge of SOD, he said, "I want you
to create the homeland security
capabilities that we need, not just in
SOD, but across the whole department."
So he gave me a blank check to create a
brand new
police philosophy in the Metropolitan
Police Department. So we created the
Homeland Security Counterterrorism
Bureau. We created CBR&. My first year
we got $17 million in funding to buy
level A suits to send our people down to
Andison, Alabama. I went down to
Andison, Alabama. I trained in sarin and
VX live sarin and VX gas. We were
trained to do rescues in hot zones. We
went down to Nevada and trained on rad
environments, radiological environments.
I was one of the few people that was
fortunate enough to train with Ken Albec
and Bill Patrick, two bioweapons
scientists, one from Russia and one from
the US, taught my bio weapons class, you
know, how to respond to biological
threats. Anthrax, right? We had anthrax
in Washington DC. These are all things
that I was on the front end of creating
and I got to go through all of that
training and all of that experience with
my whole team and the Metropol Police
Department when we were finished that
six years of of evolution was a
completely different place.
>> Wow. This is a good time to I think come
back to something I kind of promised to
listeners that we would revisit
and it goes all the way back. We're not
gonna go
all the way back to Mount Pleasant. But
when you were first day on the job, five
days, and you're looking at it and
you're thinking to yourself, we're not
doing this the right way, right? We
can't even communicate with these
community members. Furthermore, we're
not even trying to set the message
straight. And then if we flash forward,
you know, I have notes that are a bit
scattered here, but I have notes on
embracing technology, right? So this is
from governing.com. I want to give
credit where credit is due, but this
relates to looking for new ways to
connect the community to the police in
the case of the police. So the creation
of an anonymous text tip line, cleverly
named 50411. Am I saying that the right
way?
>> Give the 50.
>> Give the 50. the 411, right?
>> The 50. I'm such an idiot. I'm such an
idiot.
>> We are the 50. Like the cop, they used
to call us the 50 back in the old days.
And 411, you know, the 411.
>> Yeah. Right. So, in in 2008, they
received 292 tips. By the end of 2011,
that number had jumped to 1,200.
>> 1,200. Yeah. We got up to about 2,800.
>> 2,800. Right. And there are many
examples of how that ended up being
valuable. And then there's a whole
separate topic which is maybe related
but different which is cultivating
sources right so like developing sources
>> getting to know people and this is
quoting from the same piece but you you
treat people with respect you establish
relationships and god you know I'm
trying to think of some [snorts] of
these examples that I read about
separately but this seems to all
probably feed into a lot of what you
were doing in bad overhaul later, right?
>> Yes.
>> And I'm just wondering if you have any
other examples of [snorts] sort of
cultivating a access to helpful
information, right? Not just drowning in
noise. I'm wondering how you even
thought about that cuz I imagine one of
the challenges at at that time, probably
even still today, but especially post
911 in the wake of that, that there's
kind of a good news bad news situation.
If you want more information or tips,
there's probably going to be an
overwhelming amount depending on how you
solicit and how you search for it. So,
how did you how did you think of
separating signal from noise?
>> For me, it was pretty simple and it does
go back to Mount Pleasant. Again, pretty
intuitive on your part not having been
in policing. So when I became the chief
of police, a couple of commitments I
made to myself and to the community was
that we had a tendency to place higher
value on some neighborhoods and some
crimes than others. And our job is to
protect all of the community and every
crime should be equally important to us.
If if we're not preventing crimes, we're
not being successful making arrests. We
used to publish our arrest stats every
year and go, "Oh, look, we made 50,000
arrests last year. Look how successful
we are." Well, that's 50,000 times and
we didn't do our job because we didn't
prevent those crimes from happening. So,
to me, arrest stats are not a good
measure of success for a police
department. Now, I don't have a stat to
tell you what I prevented, right? But
the goal should be to try and prevent.
So, for me, what was very clear is when
I first took over as chief, I promised I
was going to go on the scene of every
single homicide. Why? because I wanted
people in the communities to know it
didn't matter what neighborhood you
lived in or what the circumstances of
that homicide was, that homicide's just
as important to us as every other
homicide. So, a homicide in Georgetown,
right, in the very expensive wealthy
neighborhood, if there was a homicide
there, it would get news coverage for
weeks and police were all over it and
and almost always those crimes would be
closed. But if there was a homicide in a
project, public housing project, it got
little to no news coverage. Three people
shot last night in Southeast. That was
it. That's all you'd hear. And nothing
about those people or what happened with
those crimes. And they very rarely got
closed. So I put an emphasis on trying
to cultivate those relationships in the
community. It was clear to me two
things. People didn't trust us. They
didn't trust the police. And we didn't
close these homicides because people
weren't witnesses wouldn't come forward.
They wouldn't come forward because they
didn't trust us. And so we had to change
that. So I had a great example. I was
out, we did a crime initiative during
the summer called All Hands on Deck. So
I was out on All Hands on Deck. I'm
walking through a public housing complex
and there's two middle-aged women
sitting on a wall outside in the summer.
They're drinking. They got open
containers of alcohol, which is illegal,
right? They could have been in the old
days when I was pleasing, we would just
walk over and handcuff them, lock them
up, take them to the station, right?
That's open container alcohol. So I go
over and I sit down and start talking to
him. There had been a series of
shootings in this complex and I said,
"Hey," she's like, "I don't know why you
guys are here. You don't care about us."
Kind of giving me the lip.
>> And I said, "Okay, well, I'll tell you
what. Here's my business card. My cell
phone number's on here." First of all,
they had no idea I was a chief.
>> That's [clears throat] I'm just a cop,
right? Right.
>> They don't watch the local news. They
don't know that I'm the chief. Here's my
business card. If you have any
information and you want to talk to me
about anything that's going on here and
tell me who's out here shooting in the
middle of the night, hit these kids that
are on the basketball court, please let
me know. And when I walk over to the two
ladies, they kind of take their beer,
you know, and stick it behind the wall.
I was like, you know, you're not
supposed to be drinking out here, but
I'm going to pretend I didn't see that,
right? So, so I give them my business
card. I give them that respect. I Yes,
ma'am. No, ma'am. Talk to them with a
little respect. I give them my business
card. My cell phone number's on there.
About two weeks later, I get a call at
1:00 in the morning and it was a woman's
voice. Don't know if it was those women.
Can't prove it. Don't know to this day.
But I get a call about 1:00 in the
morning. There was a shooting in that
neighborhood. And the woman's voice said
to me, "Tell your officers that the gun
is behind the white Escalade."
>> And I like, "What are you talking
about?" She says, "On Cloud Street." She
gave me that the address on Cloud
Street. She said, "There's a white
Escalade. The gun is there." So, I
turned on my police radio, half asleep,
switched to the sixth district that
where that address is. And sure enough,
they're working a shooting. And I went
over the radio. I said, "Cruiser one,
who's the onseene official? Have him
call me." He calls me. I said, "Look, I
just got a tip from somebody that
there's a gun involved in this case, and
this is where the gun is."
>> Sure enough, that's where the gun was.
They recovered that gun. From that
recovery of that gun, they were able to
start working this case and actually get
information. So, I always tie that back
to I strongly believe that the fact that
I walked over to those women. I showed
them a little respect. I sat on the wall
with them. I didn't lock them up for the
Oakland DL. They weren't hurting
anybody.
>> Mhm.
>> I sat and chatted with them. I gave them
my cell number and said, "Look, I want
to help, but if you don't give me
information, I can't help." So, that's
the philosophy that I wanted all of my
cops to have. That's the way I wanted
all of us to police our communities. I
wanted people to see that you give me
information, you'll see results. You
tell me who's involved in shooting up
the neighborhood, we'll go after them.
we will make. So we started we're doing
instead of just putting posters up when
a homicide occurred when we made an
arrest for the homicide we went back and
put posters up saying the case is closed
right reverse canvas like instead of
just telling you when something bad
happens we're going to tell you when we
close it. So now people know
>> that we've taken that person off the
street and those little things matter.
>> Yeah. Matter a lot. I want to please
confirm or deny this, but I am in the
course of speaking with you and
certainly in the course of doing
homework for this conversation impressed
with your attention to detail, which
comes back also to my signal versus
noise cuz I'm like, I am dazzled by your
ability to
manage all of these details. And I tell
me if this is a complete dead end, but
it seems like you demonstrated this
really really early on. And we'll we'll
come back to where we were in the
timeline, but this is as a you had a job
at 16 as a secretary at a commercial
real estate firm.
>> Am I getting that right?
>> Yes. Eisinger Kilbane.
>> You handle tenant billing, right?
>> Y
>> and it seems like you've practiced this
or just had this ability that you've
honed over time. you know, thousands of
pieces of correspondents come through
the police department every day, but
you're also talking about learning, I
think, at that job to never let anything
that's got your name on it be imperfect.
And it's just like, [laughter]
>> sound familiar, Tim?
>> Well, yes, there's that also. My
incredibly helpful slash
>> OCD.
>> Yeah. Brain damage and two saying OCD.
[laughter]
But as you have a job that increases in
scope upon scope upon scope upon scope
and
how do you build systems that help you
to keep track of these things, right?
Because not everyone is going to have
necessarily your
[snorts]
eye for detail or capacity to remember
the details in that photograph that
flash for a fraction of time that you
then need to recall. So, it seems like
ultimately, and I'm I am cheating a
little bit because you know when when
you sent and we asked for some notes in
advance of this conversation. I'll just
I'll just read one thing here because
>> I don't remember now. So, I got you're
going to get me on this.
>> Oh, I'll tell you. It's great. It just
says, "No hacks for me. I try to focus
on systems or strategies that will hold
up over time." Right. And I'm wondering,
for instance, whether it's in your
current role or where we left off in
terms of your timeline
as you're soliciting information from
[snorts] the community and they're
offering more because you're showing not
just the announcement of the bad thing,
but that you actually took action
related to their help that closed cases,
etc., etc. How do you ensure that the
department or
the organization that you're a part of
is equipped to digest that? And
[clears throat] I'm not sure that's an
easy question to answer, but I'll just
leave it there.
>> No, it's not an easy question to answer,
but I would say this. I experienced in
200.
So, I I pushed technology very very hard
once I became the chief. When I took
over as the chief, we had Teletubby
pagers. We didn't even have cell phones.
And I wanted everybody to have
smartphones. the early smartphones. The
first one we got was a trio.
>> We had pump pilots and trios, right? If
you remember that far back.
>> Sure, I do.
>> And then we pushed putting computers in
the cars and we pushed the technology,
gunshot detection technology, cameras,
integrating those gunshot detection
technologies, cameras, all those things
together. I really wanted technology to
be those systems, right? Taking all this
great technology that's coming out, make
us more effective and more efficient as
police officers, right? Instead of
spending three hours handwriting an
accident report, we could pull up on the
scene of an accident report, have a iPad
or a laptop in the cruiser, that GPS
drops the intersection on a police
report and all I got to do is plink a
little car down there and my police
report now takes 10 minutes instead of
two hours. Right? So, I brought all this
technology and the systems that made us
better. It made us more effective and I
relied a lot on people. I mean,
everything I did, I learned from the
people that work for me and the people
in the community. I made it a point to
go out and talk to people and listen.
Everything I learned about fighting
crime that was effective, I got it from
walking around the community and giving
my cell phone number out, listening to
what people had to say. Cuz if you
listen to people, they will tell you
what to do. and my officers, my
detectives, my sergeants, my
lieutenants, those guys. When I did my
strategic planning sessions, I would
bring in from all of those groups and,
you know, brainstorm with them, what are
the things we need? How can we do
better? What do you need that you don't
have? What are the crime trends that
you're seeing? But I witnessed this
evolution of technology and crime. And
we had to get our police department to
adjust to meet that evolution, right? We
didn't we hire cops for a 25 year
career. And when this technological
crime evolution was happening, we had
detectives that didn't know how to
manage a crime scene with seven
different cameras they had to download
to get video of the crime scene. They
didn't know how to mobiley forensically
dump a phone. You arrest a guy who just
did some armed robberies, right? And the
biggest case, and I'm sure you in your
research, you saw this Thomas Maslin
case. There was a case that really kind
of set this in stone for me. This poor
gentleman who was robbed for his cell
phone one night. He's beaten with a
baseball bat. They crush his skull. They
take his phone. Those same suspects, we
find Mr. Maslin the next day with his
skull crushed, barely alive, no cell
phone. We don't know where his cell
phone is. He's in the hospital. Well,
what we don't know is that same night,
right after they robbed him, that same
group of kids went to Adam's Morgan,
another neighborhood, and they robbed
three more people, and they were
arrested. And when they were arrested,
they had multiple cell phones on them.
They were robbing people for their cell
phones because they were going to go and
turn those phones in and make money. And
all those cell phones were recovered as
evidence and put on the books, but
nobody knew that Thomas Maslin's phone
was in that books because we didn't have
anybody that had the digital forensic
skill to dump those phones and figure
out whose phones they were. And when we
finally did figure that out months
later, I said, "This is never going to
happen again.
>> We need to have people that are trained
to have that skill. And if we can't
train our detectives to do it or we they
don't have the bandwidth to do it, then
we're going to hire civilians to do it.
But we're going to have that skill and
we're going to have it out on the street
daily." And so we did we hired criminal
research specialists. We hired some
other civilians for for digital
forensics. So we went through this
evolution and it is building systems
that will endure over time and policing
was not designed that way. So we had to
really change the way we do policing and
now police departments are are doing
much better at keeping pace with
technology. Before we get to maybe the
differences between
your experience in law enforcement
and everything that preceded the NFL and
the NFL, could you just give people an
idea of the scope of your
responsibilities at the NFL? What are
you responsible for?
>> Everything related to security. So,
executive protection, I set the
standards for physical security and
cyber security at the stadiums. So all
of the stadiums, the 30 stadiums across
the US and our international stadiums, a
little bit variation on the
international, but across all the US
stadiums, we set the requirements for
security that they have to meet. So once
we set that standard, we update it
annually. We do the audits and red
teaming and we make sure that they are
meeting those standards. So physical
security, cyber security, both. We also
have investigative responsibilities. So
violations of the personal conduct
policy, those are all investigations
that are done by my team. We have game
integrity. So, management of the game
integrity program. So, making sure that
we are maintaining the integrity of this
game.
>> There's a a lot involved in that. If
it's got anything to do with security,
it falls on us. Individually, the league
office has full responsibility for Super
Bowl, Pro Bowl, combine, draft, and all
the International Series games. So when
I say we have nine international games
this year, the reason scheduling this is
so hard. Each one of those international
games I will take a team out in advance
at least two trips if not three. And
we've got nine international games this
year. And I'm also working on we plan
Super Bowl about 18 months out in
advance because that's 10 days of events
over 20ome venues. And then draft. So
draft I'm leaving for Pittsburgh on
Sunday to go manage the draft for the
next seven or eight days. So special
events, 10 pull events, that's a big big
part of it.
>> Yeah. So tons of free time. I'm
>> tons of free time. [laughter]
>> 170 days on the road last year.
>> Oh my lordy. So red teaming is a really
critical concept that I want people to
understand. Some folks may recognize it
within the context of say tech given the
types of people that I've interviewed
before.
>> Yeah. in terms of paying people to try
to break into your systems, let's just
say, or to take down your service or to
fill in the blank, but they're on your
side. I wonder where red teaming I
should know this comes from as well.
>> Military
>> military pretending to be the Soviets,
right? Probably
>> it's the military. I mean, it was a
military concept initially. And think
about it this way. You got to look at it
a little differently. I think on the
tech side it is a little different but I
think of red teaming as we set a
standard like we think use of
magnetometers to screen for weapons. We
think use of a perimeter to make sure
everybody goes through screening. All
these standards we put in place of
security, right? I can go and audit you
and you have all those standards in
place. But what a red team operation
does is it's quality assurance. Are
those standards working? Did I tell you
to do something that didn't necessarily
work? So it tells you if the standards
that you were using are effective or
not? Maybe that you put them in place,
but you didn't execute them properly, so
they're not effective. So if you're not
properly doing secondary screening, it's
not that the magnetometers didn't work.
It's that your guard didn't respond
properly to an alert. Right? So it's a
quality assurance. That's a quality
assurance test to see if the standards
that you are employing or you're
requiring are being used properly and
are they effective. That's the key. It's
not a gotcha. It's like
>> is what we're doing effective and if
it's not effective, how can we make it
effective? How are your responsibilities
or your job with the NFL most different
from what you did beforehand? I'm just
uh imagining there might be new
constraints, what you can or can't do,
even though you're coordinating with
federal, state, and local law entities.
I mean, just imagining what that entails
with 32 clubs is makes my head spin. But
how is it most different from what you
did before?
>> I'd say it's most different in terms of
its diversity. So I thought coming from
27 years in the nation's capital
managing SOD I managed every
large event protest demonstration. We
had about 2,300 a year that I was
responsible for when I was there
[laughter]
and then presidential inaugurations. I
was like this is easy. Like I can come
to the NFL. This Super Bowl thing is
going to be nothing. Like this is going
to be a walk in the park. And the
diversity here is the complexity here is
so much more. It's so much more complex
and the diversity. So, I'm not only
setting up the equivalent of a
presidential inauguration that I did
every four years before. Every year it's
Super Bowl, but the Super Bowl is more
complex. It's spread over 10 days over
26 venues and it moves every year. So,
it's in a different place. So, I've got
to build all those relationships. I've
got to learn all those new venues. I've
got to figure out security in a
completely different climate. In
Minneapolis, it was 25 below zero. Guess
what? Some technology doesn't work in
that 25 below zero. some of the things
that we do in Arizona is not going to
work in Minneapolis.
And then now with international, right,
we try and go and implement our full
suite of security standards in Madrid
and Sa Paulo and Australia and Munich,
but when we get there, 20% of what we do
is going to have to be adapted to the
local environment. Right? There's laws
and regulations and things that are
different in different countries, right?
Things that we do here, you can't do
there. Things they do there, we can't do
here. Mhm.
>> The complexity of what I do now is far
more complicated and it's far more
diverse than what I used to do.
>> And by diverse, you just mean constantly
shifting like you mentioned these
different locations with
>> there's no template. Like I can't say,
hey, you know, it's inauguration. This
is what we do for the inauguration. The
ball sites are all the same. We do the
same things. We know what to do with the
inauguration. This is every time it's
like you just take the old plan and
throw it away. Start all over.
[laughter]
Pretty much. Not completely, but pretty
much.
>> Yeah. Well, there's no shortage of
learning.
>> You don't want to start with any
assumptions. No assumptions, that's for
sure.
>> Shift gears just a little bit. I'm
wondering if
are there any books that you recommend
or resources, this doesn't have to be
within the context of the NFL, but when
I I imagine you get approached by people
who are hoping to learn from you in one
way or another, or you are just
mentoring people, right? whether that
was in policing or within the NFL or in
other contexts. Are there any books that
you recommend frequently to other
people, doesn't need to be non-fiction,
could be anything.
>> So, I'd say my favorite book of all
times, and I made it mandatory reading
for my command staff when I took over as
the chief, which was a hoot because
nobody ever made our command staff read
anything before. And I also did a book
club. I also used this book and did a
book club with the community. The
Tipping Point,
>> Malcolm Gladwell. One of my all-time
favorite reads because it forces you to
understand that no matter what your
challenge or no matter what your problem
is, goes back to problem solving.
>> Whatever the problem is you're trying to
solve, there is a tipping point. You
just have to know what that tipping
point is. And I love that book. It's a
great I've read it three times, I think.
>> It's a great book. So, that's one of my
favorites. It just makes you think
differently. What did you hope people
reading it would take away to apply?
Like how might that change how they act
on the job or think and then therefore
act on the job?
>> Well, it doesn't matter what you're
doing, what your profession is. If you
read the tipping point, the key point is
that you can turn around any situation.
You can solve any problem if you're
paying close enough attention to the
details that you can hit that tipping
point. What is the tipping point to turn
around
>> high levels of violence in a community?
What is the tipping point to
[clears throat] turn around whatever
your problem is? I would also say Blink.
Blink is another one that I only read
because I liked Malcolm Gladwell, but
Blink for people in highpaced
professions.
>> Mhm.
>> Blink is one that helps you really
evaluate how you make decisions.
>> How you rely on your instinct and your
experience and how much that matters.
So, those are two of my favorites. The
only thing I read, Tim, is stuff about
my job. I I read work stuff. Yeah.
>> So, nothing really fun. [laughter]
Well, let me come back to the I suppose
this all relates everything relates to
making decisions, but especially
kind of performing [snorts]
under extreme and sustained pressure.
And I would imagine that of course part
of the hiring process for a lot of the
people who report to you, let's just say
or within your organization, you're
already vetting for people who can
operate at a high level with sustained
pressure where they also have to be very
good at improvising when conditions
change and so on. But if you were
teaching a class to could be high school
students, college students on sort of
resilience and handling pressure, right?
Some people buckle and sometimes you
learn by buckling and then you figure
out how to approach it next time.
What would you tell them about
making decisions under pressure and
acting under pressure as opposed to
becoming paralyzed? How would you even
begin to talk to them about that?
>> I would say it's I don't care who you
are. It's not 100% instinct, right? Mhm.
>> Your body is going to react in a crisis
to what it knows. So if it's a situation
where you have trained for it or you've
thought about it or you've prepared for
it or you in your mind you've walked
through it, you're going to be in a lot
better position than if it's something
that's never crossed your mind. This is
where kind of preparedness crosses that
line. Like this is why we try and
encourage people to be prepared. know
when you walk into a building what are
the two different ways you can get out
not just the way you came in is there
other ways you can get out of this
building right
>> so everybody's going to freeze initially
I think to a certain extent if you have
no experience nothing in your brain that
your brain can go back to to to have you
act but in terms of being in a in a
workplace or a professional environment
and making decisions as a leader
>> if you have the knowledge that you need
you've done your homework you've
read everything that there is to read,
you've got your education, you've got
experience, decision- making becomes
easy, right? As each time you go up in a
different level of rank as a sergeant,
when I first made sergeant, making
decisions was a little tough at first
because I was still pretty inexperienced
myself.
>> My job was to be more well read,
understand the DC code a little better
than the patrol officer, know what case
law says. So if I didn't read that stuff
and I didn't study, I would be
uncomfortable making decisions and I
would hesitate to make decisions. We had
a lot of people that don't like to make
decisions. But the more you read, the
more you learn, the more you invest in
your knowledge, the easier it is to make
decisions. Like to me, decisions now
with all of the years I'm in 36 years in
this business and now I've again two
master's degrees. I've [snorts] studied,
I've got all this experience. decisions
for me like boom boom boom boom. So it
comes with experience. It comes with
investment of time. It comes with
preparing yourself to be able to make a
decision. And of course people will
throw things at me that I've never
experienced before. But because I have
all those other things to rely on, I can
make a decision and I feel good about
it.
>> Well, I have to imagine also this is
true in a lot of contexts outside of
security or law enforcement. certainly
applies to military but it kind of
applies everywhere which is making
decisions in the face of incomplete
information
>> right and so I'm wondering what you have
learned about that
making decisions biasing towards action
when you have incomplete information
how do you think about that
>> it happens it happens a lot especially
in first responder communities and
military like you said it happens a lot
going to have a complete picture. Again,
I think your comfort level with being
able to make those decisions is going to
fall back on. Are you qualified to make
that decision? If you feel qualified to
make the decision, sometimes I got to
make decisions without all the
information. There's two things that go
along with that. One is do the best you
can based on what you know at the time,
but know a decision has to be made. And
then if you make the wrong decision,
undo it. change it, fix it. Don't just
stick with it because you've got to be
the boss. And this is what I said. Admit
you're wrong. Change course. Go another
direction. That's where people get
tripped up. Right? When I'm making a
decision, I don't have full information.
I'm thinking to myself as I'm making
this decision, I can either go this way
or I can go that way. If I go this way,
what can go wrong? If I go this way,
what can go wrong? Okay. Now, I'm going
to go this way. If one of those things
goes wrong, consequence thinking, right?
If one of those things goes wrong,
what's my course of action then? So, if
I'm making a decision with incomplete
information, as I'm making that decision
and giving that command, I'm thinking
about how I'm going to deal with the
collateral damage if that was the wrong
decision,
>> right?
>> Because that's next. You make a bad
decision, you can't just go, "Oh, shoot.
Wow, darn." You know, [laughter]
>> tough luck.
>> You got, all right, fix it. Fix it. Fix
it. Fix it. What are you going to do
about it now? How are you going to fix
it?
Just a few more questions and then uh
let you get back to your very busy day.
If you could put this is metaphorically
speaking like a message on a billboard
or have a reminder on your desk that
everybody sees when they come in. Could
be a could be a quote, could be a
mantra, could be anything.
If you could put it on a billboard for
millions of people to see, right? What
might that be? I mean, is there anything
that comes to mind? Could be someone
else's quote. Could be something that
you try to live your life by. Could be
something you want everybody who who's
within your organization to be reminded
of
or it could be something else entirely.
Does anything come to mind?
>> I mean, I tell people all the time, bad
things happen to everybody, right?
>> Mhm.
>> Bad things happen to everybody. And a
lot of times it's we do it to oursel.
>> We make bad decisions. Bad things happen
to us because of ourselves. Bad things
happen to everybody. It's not about the
bad decision you made or the bad thing
that happened to you. It's what you do
after that.
>> So, it's easy to
have some tragedy or some terrible thing
happen to you and sit around and feel
sorry for yourself or become a victim or
let it define you. It's your attitude
and your effort that you put into how
you recover. So, it's not what happens
to you. It's not the bad thing. It's how
you handle those things that really
matter in life. [clears throat]
>> Because you can have one of two
attitudes every time something bad
happens. Which attitude are you going to
pick? For me, it's going to be I wish
that never had happened. I wish I'd
never made that decision. I wish that
had never happened. But you know what?
I'm going to fix it. I'm going to I'm
going to not let it define me. I'm not
going to let it take me down.
>> Well, Kathy, I mean, I think that's a
pretty strong way to land this plane.
So,
>> you have the coolest job, by the way. I
can't imagine how much you get to learn
talking to so many people. And
>> you must have a an encyclopedia in your
brain.
>> It's the best job. I mean, and it didn't
come from some big long-term plan. It
was kind of zigging and zagging with
frankly I mean tying into what you said
some really you know in retrospect with
the information I had at the time there
were good decisions about various things
you know starting books but made some
terrible decisions on deadlines where
there were kind of suicide missions and
ultimately just adapted and tried to
make the best of
a sequence of I would say in retrospect
kind of poor decisions led to one of the
best decisions right which I never
thought would become this and here we
are. So,
>> good for you
>> and thanks for being willing to do the
dance and uh play some improv jazz in
this conversation. Is there is there
anything else you'd like to say or add,
suggest to people, request of people?
Anything at all before we wind to a
close?
>> No, just uh was a fascinating couple
hours with you. You know, I'm an avid
follower and really enjoyed my time
here. So, thank you for including me.
Oh, definitely. Kathy, thank you so
much. I hope we get to see each other at
some point. Who knows? Might get to your
neck of the world. Probably will,
actually.
>> Please let me know if you do. New York
or DC. Look me up.
>> I'm in both. So, I'll keep you posted.
>> Okay.
>> Thank you again for the time. And for
everybody listening, we'll have show
notes, links to everything that we
talked about at tim.blog/mpodcast.
As per usual, just search for Kathy and
you will find this episode. Until next
time, be just a bit kinder than is
necessary to others, but also to
yourself. And thanks for tuning in.
>> Thanks, Tim.